uh
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to the 64th live
episode of the ask a budget show it's
very nice to be back among you
and today is a live chat session which
means that i will be taking questions
that you are asking to me
live
in the live chat
so who else do we have here i can see
lots of people
and good evening to everybody i will not
take everyone's name today
uh
before i begin i would like to thank a
couple of people
the ones who have been doing the time
stamps
so i want to thank harshit harshit 2.0
every episode he has been doing the
timestamps it's a very tedious task but
he's doing it to help all of you
and also i would like to thank akash
buller who had done that for a long time
in the past
this is a very tedious time consuming
job and it's it's a great help to all
the viewers to have specific time stamps
for every question so i want to thank
akash bhullar and harshit 2.0 for doing
this work without
without me asking for that thank you so
much guys i really appreciate that
the thing is i have been thanking them
in the comments but if you really feel
grateful you should thank them in public
you should thank
people you feel grateful for in public
so that's what i would like to do thank
you guys thank you so much
right
so now let's begin with the questions
if you have questions let's have them
let us have the questions
uh
what questions do we so i will mostly
take questions from the uh live chat but
maybe a few from the comments
because uh there were there were a lot
of questions that i had selected
yesterday i was not able to cover them
all
so maybe i will pick a few from those
there's always lots of questions and i'm
unable to answer most of them
unfortunately
so let's see what we have today
let us see
where was that question i click on
something it disappears
hang in there okay
there was okay
here is the question this is vibration
of pt
and the question is
why can't the sindhu saraswati
civilization have two languages tamil
and sanskrit listen i don't see anything
wrong with this this civilization having
10 languages
india has always been a very large
civilization lots of different language
groups
uh the civilizational language the glue
that bound the civilization together has
always been sanskrit but there have
always been lots of other languages
existing in parallel right
and that's the always been the case
throughout the length and breadth of the
indian civilization see
a thousand years ago in indonesia
sanskrit was the civilizational language
even today they consider sanskrit to be
the civilizational language and yet
their actual native language is the
bahasa indonesia pasha indonesia so even
a thousand years ago when sanskrit was
the official state language civilization
language etc the uh
vernacular language would or would would
certainly have been basha indonesia
right and similarly if you go to the
philippines you have the tagalog
language but they also had sanskrit and
so on and so forth so the point is
when you have a land mass
as large as india a subcontinent-sized
landmass you're gonna have lots of
languages that are spoken but you need
one civilizational language to bind the
entire civilization and culture together
and that has always been sanskrit
that's always been sanskrit in india
sanskrit is the oldest indo-european
language that we know of it's the oldest
language that we know of anywhere in the
world
and so i have i am sure there were lots
of languages that co-existed at the time
but the high language the the
civilization language was always
sanskrit tamil would have existed i mean
proto-tamil or something like that would
have existed and there are lots of other
languages
uh most of the languages that we speak
in india today especially in the
northern half of india western half
and also eastern half to some extent
these languages are all derived from
sanskrit but you also have a bunch of
other languages down south
that seem to have a
kind of a separate origin but possibly
so the linguistic analysis has never
been done
we only rely on the linguistic analysis
that the bishop caldwell did which was
not even a proper
proper linguistic analysis and
after his analysis no other linguist has
bothered to actually examine the roots
of the languages of southern india in in
detail ab initial properly not relying
on the bishop the good bishop you know
so that has never been done that's why
we are not quite sure what are the
origins of all the indian languages
there i am sure that every indian
language has very ancient roots
maybe they go back tens or tens of
thousands of years it's quite possible
right
india is the original founder zone of
the out of africa migration the first
place where humanity settled after
leaving africa
was india the indian subcontinent
and our
genetics have been evolving ever since
for the past 60 65 000 years maybe 70
000 years in the indian subcontinent and
so have the languages
so all of these languages most likely
have their roots right here
right in inside the indian subcontinent
uh but the oldest language that we know
of
is sanskrit
that's what i can say
so even during the sindhu saraswati
phase of india's civilization there must
have been lots of languages that were
spoken in various parts
of the geography but the civilizational
language has always been unambiguously
sanskrit
okay
let us take the next question
anish says can you speak about the depth
of knowledge of ancient indians which
they have which our
ancestors had about astronomy
for example jupiter the largest planet
is called guru in sanskrit yes
and guru means big or huge in sanskrit
i'm not sure okay maybe it does
okay what about the knowledge that we
had about astronomy so our ancestors
have been had been
studying
the heavens
the movements of the planets and the
stars etc for thousands of years and we
know that because
the oldest evidence of a supernova
explosion the oldest human recorded
evidence of a supernova explosion is
found up in northern india
uh in
the in the kashmir valley i think
and
it's a supernova that was recorded on a
stone carving so you have a stone
carving with
a couple of constellations
that are depicted there and there are
two suns in the sky
so it clearly means that one of these
suns is our actual sun the star that we
orbit around and the other one because
we only have one sun so the other one
was some celestial phenomenon which was
almost as bright as the sun so that can
only be a supernova and if you look at
the position of the supernova in this in
the in the star chart
you are actually able to go back in time
and pinpoint which supernova event it
was so it happened i think about
several thousand years before today i
don't remember the exact date
uh what we can do is we can look it up
online let's let's take a look at that
so
let's google it
uh
kashmir
supernova two sons no it's a supernova
drone six thousand years ago
so this is the
this is the uh
chart that was found in the stone
carving in kashmir's
borus site
they initially they thought it depicted
a hunting scene because there are two
guys one with a spear
and one with this bow and arrow
and they seem to be hunting these two
animals but then it was realized it was
actually a star a sky chart
constellations
and there are two suns and then when it
was uh
examined further
they did
they realized it is supernova hb9 a star
that exploded about 6 000 or 4600 bce
so that is the deal so it shows how
long ago indians were they were
studying the night sky and recording
such events
and we have a we when the greeks came to
india during uh
seleucus niketa's time when they came to
the court of our empire chandragupta
maurya they
they saw that uh the indians the ancient
indians of that time they had a calendar
that went back all the way to around uh
i don't know six thousand something bc
let me take a look at that let's find
the exact date subterrish calendar
the rishi calendar
so that goes back to 6676 bc
and
so that tells you how long indians had
been
reckoning time
and how long they had been recording
events and calendars
are always tied to astronomy
because you cannot
determine the exact length of a year of
a month etc and so on and so forth
without studying the stars the sun the
moon etc the moon's phases all that in
exquisite detail
and the indian calendar was
extraordinarily accurate accurate it was
more accurate than today's calendar the
january to december calendar the what's
it called it's not the julian calendar
it's the gregorian calendar i think it's
called
so india's ancient calendar was more
accurate than the
modern gregorian this is the gregorian
calendar let me take a look at that
gregorian
calendar yeah it is the gregorian
calendar
so that's how it was
so the depth of ancient knowledge
the depth of knowledge ancient indians
had
was
was vast it was very deep and all that
knowledge was recorded in ancient
india's universities the universities
whose libraries were burned down but
before they were burned down the arabs
etc the turks they there they send some
scholars to india who took away all the
interesting information all the
interesting texts which were then
translated into arabic
and people like al-khwarizmi etc
are now credited as great scientists and
polymaths when they were simply
translators
and they never denied the fact that they
were simply translators it is the
europeans who have interpreted these
people as great polymaths because they
wrote about all kinds of topics
astronomy physics cosmology
pharmacology toxicology linguistics and
so on and so forth mathematics
so one guy if he's able to write so much
about these topics it's clear that he is
simply a translator who is translating
texts that were extracted out of india
people like al-khwarizmi and so on and
so forth
whatever whatever the names are
so in short in brief to answer your
question is that india had incredible
depth of knowledge of astronomy i mean
all the data that was taken out of india
was then used to formulate kepler's
three law of pla of of
kepler's three law right
of planetary motion and so on so that
these are the facts
okay
they just says where the mayans and the
aztecs somehow related to india well
from what i have seen i have seen no
hard evidence that proves that they were
in any way related to india i am not
saying it's not possible
it may be possible but but so far from
the data that we have i don't know i do
not personally see a direct uh
unambiguous link with india there are
certain practices etc that are similar
to indian practices some aspects of
their culture seem to be
in some ways
uh reminiscent of indian culture they
also
the peoples of central and southern
america south america also had a very uh
a very good
calendar system they also were deep into
astronomy
and all that they had a very good
understanding of the
cycles
of the moon and the stars and the
planets and all that so
so it's clear that they are also an
ancient they were also an ancient
civilization the civilization has been
destroyed now
but uh it was an ancient civilization
and their calendar went back i don't
know
they did understand the precession of
the equinoxes which is
something that takes thousands of years
so uh it's clear from the data from the
evidence that has survived that they
were in ancient quite ancient
civilization and some of their practices
are reminiscent of indian traditions and
culture but there is no unambiguous
unequivocal linkage that proves some
kind of relationship or contact with
ancient india so that's what i can say
about this
okay shekhar siroff says
we always see the images of the galaxies
and universe as a disc form horizontally
but what's in the vertical space above
and below
uh
above and below in light ears so let's
let's uh let's take a look at what
shekhar is saying let me again share the
screen
so let's see the universe
universe and go to images
so this is the
cosmic microwave background radiation of
the universe so this is the map of the
distribution of the ancient radiation
that's left over from the big bang
uh so this is one way of looking at it
the other way is this which is
actually makes more sense
right
so
it's this is essentially how the
satellite which satellite was it
initially it was the cob kobe satellite
then you had the planck satellite that
measured uh the cmbr cosmic microwave
background radiation
and this is the map that this satellite
was these satellites were able to
produce
but there is nothing above or below it
is all this entire data is taken from
our vantage point
it's actually a spherical uh
field of view that the satellite has and
it measures everything and it is just
represented in this format
to make it easier for us to visualize
the distribution of ancient radiation
cmbr in the universe
so it's kind of represented like this
in this fashion it can also be
represented as a sphere in this manner
um
so the point is there is nothing above
or below
we this is the observable universe what
we mean by the observable universe is
that it is it tells us how far we can
see inside the universe
uh the observable universe has a radius
if you see this sphere let's see this is
the let's say this is the universe so we
are at the exact center of this sphere
it's not a it's not a disc it's a sphere
it's a three-dimensional sphere think of
it like a basketball right and we are at
the exact center of it
and we can see that far
as far as the edge of this ball
in the universe and the distance between
us and the edge is about 46.5
or so
billion light years that's how far we
can see
it doesn't mean the universe is only
this this large it may be way way way
larger than that but we are unable to
see beyond that because of the
limitations of the speed of light and
the
constraints imposed by the expansion of
the universe
so this is how it is depicted it looks
like a disc but it's actually
it's actually a three-dimensional sphere
and we are at the exact center of it
right
so there is nothing above or below what
lies beyond the boundaries of this
of this
representation is the unobservable
universe because it is gone because we
are light doesn't travel
that fast in the universe beyond these
edges is expanding too fast for us to
for the for the light from those regions
to reach us
so there may be
a much larger portion of the universe
that we are unable to see we don't know
what its size is we don't know what the
shape is we may never be able to see it
and these boundaries are still are
always receding because the universe
keeps on expanding
uh and the expansion is speeding up
so we are inside this sphere we are at
the very center of this
three-dimensional
ball and
above below it's all see there is no
above or below in space
uh
when you are out there in space beyond
the there is no up or down right left
it's all depending on what orientation
you have
uh
we
perceive the world as up and down
because of the force of gravity that
acts upon us which uh pulls us towards
the center of the earth so that's why we
have the sensation of up and down
because if we throw something up it will
come down and we know where down is in
space there is no gravity there is no up
and down right
so we are at the center of this thing
of the observable universe and its shape
is
spherical perfectly spherical and there
may be maybe much more beyond that that
we are not aware of and we may never be
able to observe those portions
of the universe
so that's what i can say about this in
brief
mr right trooper says what would happen
if a black hole reaches near the earth
at the same distance as the moon well if
a black hole were to orbit around the
earth at the same distance as the moon
it would simply mean that we have a new
satellite a new moon which happens to be
a black hole it also depends on the size
of the black hole i mean the kind of
gravitational effects that we would
experience
would depend on the size the mass the
mass of the black hole uh a black hole
with the same mass as the moon would
essentially be a very small object you
know
uh i'm not sure that what the
calculation is the schwarzschild radius
of that it would be something very small
with the mass of the moon right
uh so it would not be visible but we
would experience the uh gravitational
effects of that if it were a more
massive black hole then it would
it would have a different kind of
a different set of gravitational effects
on the earth
uh
the tides would be disrupted and so on
only if it is in orbit if it just passes
by
then the
orbit of the earth may be tugged in a
certain direction temporarily or not
temporarily or permanently essentially
if it passes by passes close by and so
on so it all depends on the dynamics
whether it is
simply passing by the earth at the
distance uh the same distance as the
moon or does it come into orbit around
the earth as the same distance of the
moon and what is the mass of the black
hole is it a small primordial
microscopic kind of black hole or is it
a more massive black hole stellar size
black hole that would disrupt the entire
dynamics of the solar system if it were
a stellar sized black hole stellar mass
black hole and so on so it depends on
the mass of the black hole the velocity
trajectory of the black hole whether it
comes into orbit around the earth
whether it pulls the earth into its
orbit whether it messes up the
orbits of the other planets and so on
and so forth so there's a lot of
uh parameters involved in this
but if it were to simply go around the
earth or go into orbit around the earth
then our
then the tidal cycles and other things
on the earth would be disrupted
you would see
uh
you would see maybe tsunamis or such
things happening maybe the tectonics of
the earth would may also be affected by
that you may
see
an increase in volcanism you may see an
increase in earthquakes
and so on and so forth
so
that's what i can say in brief about
this
this is by chanakya
how do we get out of the defeatist
mindset that permeates indians and how
can we turn this around after hundreds
of years of defeats how to gain the
momentum to be glorious so i spoke about
momentum yesterday
uh
we are currently experiencing
a certain kind of momentum the past 1000
years have not been very good for india
we resisted the invasions for a very
long time but eventually the momentum
went in the favor of the turks
later the marathas were able to kick the
turks out of power and regain most of
india established hinduism
all the way up to southern afghanistan
but then they also made mistakes and
again the momentum turned in the wrong
direction
and the british were able to take over
india and today we are under a system
of governance of education etc that is
entirely 100 colonial in nature and that
is essentially the root cause
of the slave-mindedness and defeatism
that we see all around us people and it
is not the fault of the people for
holding these beliefs it is these
beliefs are drilled into children's
heads for years because of the education
system that's what the education system
does that's what the textbooks do that
was that's what the teachers do the
teachers themselves are the same mindset
because they also went through the same
education system and that is
perpetuating
this momentum
we are not taught what is the national
interest we are not taught what is
leadership
we are not taught the correct history of
india we are taught to worship and
glorify the invaders the barbarians who
destroyed indian civilization
uh
our institutions are all colonial in
nature we have district collectors what
are they collecting i ask what does a
district collector collect
the entire governance system is colonial
in nature they have not even changed the
names they still call these individuals
collectors
what are they collecting
what does the district collector collect
so unless
we reform the the all of this we are
going to persist in this defeatist
mindset we are still going to going to
feel that foreigners are superior to us
indians have inferior genetics i don't
blame anybody for holding these beliefs
that white skin is superior in some way
uh if you speak english with a certain
accent then you are more intelligent
than other people
have you noticed something
in school
if you ask a question to your teacher
with with incorrect grammar your
question will not be entertained
right
so they equate intelligence with good
grammar in english and and the right
kind of accent if you speak english with
a foreign accent then you are
automatically uh regarded as being more
intelligent than
regular indians
and so on and so forth so all these
attitudes are creating this defeatist
mindset that our culture is inferior our
accents are are
a sign of backwardness
and all of these things so how do we
change the momentum we have to reform
the entire indian governance and
education system we have to throw out
the colonial constitution
and create and
build and draft a new consideration that
is indian
in nature indian in values indian in
principles
not western in its morality and values
and principles and all that
so that's what needs to happen all of
our institutions need to be reformed i
mean certain institutions are so deeply
colonial they go on vacation i don't
know how many months in a year
and so on i i suppose you can understand
what that is
all of our
other institutions i mean
the the
westminster parliamentary system that we
have it is not suitable it is not suited
for a subcontinent subcontinent size
country we had our own form of democracy
which was superior we need to go back to
that
we need to reform the education system
the education system is i mean somebody
asked me one in one of the comments i'd
seen they said that uh students
in one of the comments today itself i
saw it
that students only learn how to pass
exams they don't really acquire any real
knowledge and why is it so it's because
if you don't pass your exam you're not
allowed to progress to the next level in
in the education system and unless you
have a degree you will not get a job in
the country so you have to the only
skill you really acquire is how to pass
exams
and and do well in exams you don't
really acquire any real knowledge or any
real skills of any other kind in the
education system and
the history you're taught is all
defeatist history
that says that the foreigners were great
and indians were losers so all of this
has to be changed when will it happen
unless we change it if we don't change
it we are never going to be
we are never going to turn our mindset
around
i mean that's the thing right if you
tell a child every single day of his or
her life for the power for the first 20
years of their life that you are you
come from a culture of losers you come
from a nation of losers your ancestors
were losers your culture was inferior
then that's what they will believe
that's what they will believe and such
people such kids can never be leaders
if you believe i mean i mean remember
remember what that guy
imran khan
and he was proud of it
imran khan the prime minister of
pakistan was proud of the fact that
turks ruled over his people
for i don't know how many years he said
thousand years or so
and by his people i mean india
he was also his ancestors were also
indians so he was proud of the fact that
a foreign race ruled over his people for
centuries
this is the kind of leadership we are
throwing up i mean pakistan also is
representative of the same mindsets that
we have in india and we have plenty of
indians with the same mindset
and they feel proud of being of the fact
that the turks and the british ruled
over india for such a long time
oh the british gave us so much so much
so much they gave us railways they gave
us the judiciary
they gave us the english language
education without english there is no
science
such utter nonsense so unless we reform
the system
nothing is going to change so my
question is when is the reform starting
when are we going to start the reforms
so that's what needs to happen in brief
okay what
i see a very good question
tejas says why did the wh o skip skip
one of the greek letters of the alphabet
while naming the new kovid variant
so let's take a look at the greek
alphabet shall we
okay greek alphabet
let's take okay let me
yeah here we are the greek alphabet and
let's find it
all right
where is kai
okay
so they have been naming the various
kovid variants after letters of the
greek alphabet because everything has to
be eurocentric so alpha beta gamma delta
epsilon zeta eta all that
and i think the latest variant they had
named was named the new new variant
and
what comes after new
it is the letter
zai
which is spelled as x i in the latin
alphabet or the english alphabet x i now
x i is also the name of the great prime
m the great chinese emperor mr xi
jinping
and that's why
the w h o
skipped
this letter
and name the new variant omicron
instead of naming it
zai
or kai
zaya thinks i
so it is
clearly because of chinese pressure that
they have done this because
to name the new variant the shi variant
you know the
the emperor of china mr xi jinping would
not like it
and it looks like the who has now been
entirely taken over by the chinese
i mean the chinese fund
don't quite give give it quite a lot of
funding the americans are the major
funders of the who in the u.n
but clearly the chinese have way more
influence now in the un and the who than
the americans it's a complete takeover
they have infiltrated every nook and
cranny of this organization
and
you will see that the officials the
highest ranking officials of the who etc
they are so differential towards china
and they will never entertain anything
that uh the chinese would find offensive
like uh
like even mentioning the name of taiwan
right so that tells you
what a great job the chinese have done
of taking over this international
organization so that is the reason why
the who skipped one of the letters
for the first time of the greek alphabet
in naming the new kovid variant it is
out of deference
to the
emperor of china mr xi jinping
incredible
akshay prakash says why is the indian
navy being so ignored all the time how
can we strengthen the indian navy and
how can it be how can we increase the
rate
of increasing military weapons well i
would not uh say that
the navy is being ignored i would not
say that it's being ignored but
uh it is not being developed to the
extent that it should be developed
uh we do see the regular induction of
new scorpene submarines into the indian
navy
uh recently the new aircraft carrier is
being trialled it's it's the
the sea trials have started so these
things are happening but
i don't know who
makes the decisions
see let's take a look at the map let me
open the map
one second let me share that
uh
here's the map
here is the map and this is the indian
ocean region as you can see india is
blessed by the gods it has such an
incredibly long coastline it practically
dominates the entire indian ocean region
it uh dominates the two choke points
uh which three choke points actually the
persian gulf the the strait of hormuz
over here
then you have
the
the djibouti strait over here
and the malacca strait over here so
india is in a position to close off
any of these choke points if it so
wishes if it has a powerful navy
and in this in the case
if it wants to
impose a blockade on any of these stroke
points it will need numbers
you need large numbers of of naval
vessels to do that
and currently this strength in numbers
of the indian navy isn't isn't anything
great you know
and i know somebody or the other will
say no you are wrong we have so many
ships i mean actually take a look at how
many warships we have out of those
numbers
the actual number of warships is is
quite less
we have
other kinds of ships like
tankers and various other minesweepers
maybe a couple of minesweepers but how
many destroyers do we have we have just
a handful of destroyers how many missile
boats do we have smaller ships very few
how many corvettes do we have very few
how many submarines do we have i think
15 or 16 active submarines
for a country of india's size
which calls the indian ocean region its
strategic backyard you need a far larger
navy
and the problem is we are investing in
enormous ships like aircraft carriers
there is a very old saying in the
military
that quantity has a quantity has a
quality of its own you may want to build
ships of the best quality which will
cost billion dollars or you can instead
of doing that invest in 100
cheaper ships
the total cost will be 100 will be a
billion dollars but each of these ships
can carry a few missiles and that can
totally change the dynamics of the
indian ocean region if india does that
but india is not doing that we are
investing in these big big big ships you
know which say hey look at this big
target
aircraft carriers and all that india
should invest in cheaper ships lots of
cheaper ships invest in quantity forget
about the quality right now i'm not
saying you
invest in low quality hips i'm saying
invest in large numbers of ships
and you don't need big ships a missile
boat will do so these are the things
that need to happen if you want to
dominate the indian ocean region you
need numbers you need quantity
that's what the chinese are doing
quantity they're they're
churning out ships like sausages in a
factory so india also needs to do that
that's how we can strengthen the indian
navy i would say
build lots of missile boats small ships
that carry 203 missiles through three
brahmos missiles and fill up the indian
ocean with the ships
one ship need not cost more than 30 40
million dollars so you can build a
hundred of these for just four billion
dollars and that that will that is the
price of one aircraft carrier
so that's what we should do and we
should also have lots of submarines
13 or 14 or 15 16 20 submarines is
simply not enough
for a nation of india's size with the
kind of
uh strategic
advantage we have
potential
so we are the indian government is
in a way strengthening the indian navy
we are trialing the new aircraft carrier
we are inducting submarines from time to
time but it is not happening at the pace
that is required
and india is investing in big big big
ships instead of investing in large
numbers of smaller ships which are
equally dangerous
so
i think
we need a change in mindset the problem
is that the leadership
will have their own
perception of the world
what what really is needed
is lots of young leaders who see the
world from a 21st century
viewpoint not from the cold war
viewpoint you know but
so there are challenges i hope that
something will be done about this
and that's what i can say
so it's a good question
okay let's
some more questions
okay bowan says will the majority of the
population of the world is it going to
be unemployed around the globe due to
rising technology there is certainly a
possibility there is going to be more
unemployment in the next five to 10
years you are going to see the emergence
of the metaverse we're going to see
uh ai become even more powerful
everything will be automated more and
more uh
un low skill
jobs will become automated
robotics is already there it's taken
over the assembly lines and everything
you don't need
lots of workers in factories anymore
much of the work can be done
by uh
assembly robots and all that
and much of the unskilled or low skilled
work can now be automated
using apps and software and ai
for instance in indian metropolitan
cities you still if you want to buy a
train ticket you still have to go
physically to the railway station
stand in a god damn long queue
and
pay the money and and buy the ticket
that is going to be automated very soon
so
so all these jobs will soon be
eliminated they will not be required
anymore so what's going to be
important in the future is that you need
to be really good at high technology you
need to be comfortable with learning new
technology quickly and new skills
quickly it's all going to be about
skills
and certain specific skills are going to
be in high demand
uh
and all other skills
or or
general skills etc will no longer be
needed so the indian education system
throws out students by the million
students who have no skills whatsoever
you may have a degree in computer
science
yeah a master's degree in computer
science but when you go and actually get
a job you will have to be taught
everything from scratch because you are
the only skill you you really learned in
your in acquiring your master's degree
is how to pass exam how to write write
long essays and yeah there may be one or
two small projects you would do but
those are worthless actually so you
don't really learn any real skills in
the indian education system and in the
next five to ten years all of these
degrees are going to be worthless scraps
of paper
today as of today the indian
private institutions the private
companies etc they still value degrees
very much if you have a degree then you
will get a job but in the future that's
not going to be
the case in the us you have people like
elon musk who are now saying we don't
care about your degree show us your
skills
if you apply for a job in tesla or
wherever in elon musk's companies they
are simply going to put you through a
number of coding tests and other
interview questions
and you will have to prove
that you have the right skills even if
you don't even have a college degree or
even a high school degree it won't
matter as long as you have the skills so
that's the direction in which silicon
valley is going that's the direction in
which companies like tesla are going
sooner or later
it's going to happen in india it is
going to be sooner rather than later
especially
in newer startups newer unicorns the
older companies that are run by old men
they are going to stay the same their
mindset will stay the same and they are
soon going to go out of existence
it is the new agile nimble companies
that will put
more emphasis on skills rather than on
degrees
so people who rely on degrees are going
to be jobless in the future
wake up my friends listen to what i'm
saying acquire skills acquire skills
that are going to be of value in the
next 10 20 years
that's how you're going to be remain
relevant in in in the world and be
valuable drivers of change
so that's the situation we are going
towards lots of people are going to be
unemployed especially in poorer
countries low income countries third
world countries much of africa maybe all
of africa
may
uh
fall prey to this much of india will
fall prey to this because even today as
of today in 2021 it's all about degrees
degrees degrees study studies study past
examples past exam past exam acquire a
degree go on to the next level do the
same thing repeat the process at the end
of your academic career you have a
master's degree or mba or something like
that or maybe a phd which actually is
not an indicator of any kind of ability
right
so yes people are going to be unemployed
is going to be a big problem people are
talking about universal basic income
which
in my opinion is not the right solution
so yeah we are heading towards a period
of maybe of increasing turmoil and the
social
strife possibly in the future as
this becomes more widespread
so i would urge you
to uh that i'm not saying don't acquire
degrees certainly you should acquire
degrees because as of today degrees in
the next five years may still be
valuable
if you want a job today if you then you
will need a degree but in the future
it's going to be about skills so spend
some extra time acquiring
skills
valuable skills you know what those
skills are go for that
okay let's take some more questions what
do we have what do we have
what's my take on the flat earth theory
it's wrong we know it's wrong
what other take do you expect me to have
shirima bhagavad
the song of the lord the song of god
it's bhagavad-gita it's not
bhagavad-gita
so first of all let me clarify that and
secondly i don't know if the
bhagavad-gita speaks about the
the geometry of the three-dimensional
geometry of the earth the bhagavad gita
was about
waking that guy arjun up who had decided
not to fight
so it's it was more about that about you
what doing your duty and forgetting
about the what the the results of the
actions do your duty and don't abdicate
your duty that's what lord krishna was
telling arjuna
so i think that's what it was about i
don't think it was about the geometry
of the earth
the geography of the earth so
so i don't know what to
make of that if there is anything
uh
relevant to the
shape of the earth in the bhagavad-gita
but please remember it's not the
bhagavad-gita it's the bhagavad-gita
says is there any genetic proof that the
yamnaya people had indian ancestry the
yamnaya
haplogroup
so the haplogroup the y y chromosomal
that most the overwhelming majority of
the omni skeletons carry
is r1 b
r1b is a descendant of r1
r1 is a descendant of r
and r eventually
has f as its ancestor
so all of these haplogroups are indian
origin haplogroup they evolved they
emerged in the indian subcontinent
including r and r1
right
so the yamnya
where of indian origin
now the the other question people ask is
that if the yamnaya were of indian
origin why don't we find the r1b
haplogroup in india actually we do find
it in small numbers not in large numbers
we do find it in india now the
thesis the claim of the rn inversion
theory is that the yamnia were the rn
invaders who came into india and
populated and seeded india with their
genes so then the question is why don't
we have a widespread distribution of r1b
in india
instead we find only a few traces of r1b
in india just a few percent maybe two
three percent possibly i don't know have
the exact numbers but it's a very small
distribution
of r1b in india we do find it but not in
large numbers
what actually most likely happened was
that at some point in time one clan one
group of people
one extended family of people where went
out of india for whatever reason maybe
it happened during the
the the battle of the ten kings or maybe
at some later date
and they went north west of india out of
india they settled down in central asia
or somewhere like that and eventually
they became the so-called yamnia who
invaded
europe and changed the genetics forever
that's why we find r1b which is
widespread in europe not in india but we
do find evidence of r1b in india in
small numbers
so there is genetic proof they are
trying to deny it they are trying to
deny it's not going to work
the genetic evidence is there
they are trying to interpret it
in
different ways but the
most parsimonious and straightforward
explanation is that the yamnya went out
the ancestors of the yamnaya were
indians it was one
group or one clan of ancient indians who
went out of india settled down somewhere
in central asia
and from there at a later point in time
their descendants invaded europe
and gave rise to the modern european
population so that is the most
parsimonious explanation in genetics the
most part submunous explanation is
the most
acceptable explanation it's the most
straightforward explanation the shortest
distance between two points is a
straight line not
something like that
right that's how it works
okay let's take some more questions
shaker says i have read in ncaart that
the indian consideration is one of the
most successful constitutions in the
world how true is the statement okay
so there is a statement which says
that the indian constitution is the most
successful constitution or one of the
most successful constitutions in the
world
okay
so then the question we have to ask
is
what is the measure of the success of a
constitution
success has to be
measurable
what is the measure
there is no measure of the success of a
constitution
just because it has been in force for 70
years doesn't mean it's successful look
at the situation in india today
70 years after independence india is
still a low income nation
right
india is still
well technically a third world country
so is that i mean that that is
statistics that we have
what is the per capita gdp in india it's
very low
india is still
uh one of is it's still not in the top
three in the world in terms of overall
gdp
so where is the measure where is the
evidence of the success of the
constitution
a constitution is supposed to drive a
country forward and and help it succeed
and prosper the indian constitution has
not done that
if you look at the uh
so so i mean the point i'm trying to
make is that there is no evidence
measurable quantifiable evidence
that the indian constitution is
successful they have not defined what
they mean by success
it is just the subjective statement they
have made to brainwash kids the indian
constitution is the most i mean
it's it's hundreds of pages long
nobody even constitution ex
constitutional experts are unable to
agree about it if you ask
two so-called constitutional experts
about the interpretation of some clause
both will typically disagree about it
there are it is so subjective it is so
open to interpretation it is so
confusing so convoluted
that i don't know what purpose it serves
ask anybody you know
have you read the entire indian
constitution and i know what the answer
is going to be
ask them if you have read 10 percent of
the indian constitution in in depth i
know what the answer is going to be
nobody reads it because nobody
understands it
and
that's the thing right so it is not
the constitution that india needs india
needs to revert to its civilizational
roots
india needs a new constitution that is
rooted in india's civilizational roots
values and principles
this the constitution that we have is a
foreign imposition upon india
the so-called constituent assembly
did not represent the people of india it
was not
an elected body it was an appointed body
it was it was up it was appointed from
the results of the 1946 i think election
which which uh in which less than 13
percent of india's adults were able to
participate
so it is in no way representative of the
actual will of the people at that time
and even
and some other members of this
constituent assembly were simply
appointed from various royal so-called
princely states and all many of whom
were simply british puppets
so
it was an illegitimate body the
constitution has been imposed upon the
people of india by saying we the people
when it does not represent we the people
and it was never ratified by the people
of india for instance
when the u.s constitution was drafted it
was put to a vote every
may every white male in america
was given the choice of saying yes i
accept it or no i reject it
and only when it was
accepted by a majority of the white men
in america only then did it come to
power
of course the women were excluded from
the votes
from the voting and the native americans
and blacks were also excluded so it is a
white men's constitution but at least
there was a democratic process a partial
democratic process process
when the indian constitution was drafted
why was it not put to a vote why were
the people of india not given the option
of rejecting or accepting the
constitution
it was never done
and therefore it is illegitimate
it is undemocratically imposed upon
india so i don't see first of all how
this constitution is legitimate i don't
see secondly how it represents the will
of the people of india and thirdly i
don't see what
in what way it is successful
yeah you could say it has succeeded in
keeping the country down
that is the success i would say
so
that's what i can say about this
sarcastic junkies
nice name brother
it says please elaborate on doctor whom
you baba's death assassin is an
assassination conspiracy so dr baba was
the
one of the primary scientists in the
indian nuclear program
uh
and he died in a mysterious plane crash
in the swiss out through the italian
alps somewhere between switzerland and
italy
let's go to the map let's take a look at
the map
let's go westwards
we have switzerland here
let's take a look at the satellite
imagery
so this is switzerland
and
yes so this is the region
where france switzerland and italy
converge it is somewhere around here
that the plane crash occurred high in
the
alps in the mountains over here and for
many decades there was no investigation
done over here the
wreckage was never investigated nobody
went there to recover the wreckage or to
record the bodies
and that's very strange the indian
government also never insisted that
anything should be done
the indian government just accepted
this as something that's well par for
the course okay murgaya martindo that
sort of attitude
so uh i have heard rumors
i don't know how true they are that this
was a targeted assassination it was fine
to kill lots of people as long as this
indian scientist also died
i don't know how true or false that is
but it's certainly something that i've
heard
on the grapevine you could say
there is no confirmation of this
but it is certainly possible that this
was a targeted assassination
there are many such
possibilities the other possibility is
that the the the death of uh prime
minister shastri
may also have been a targeted
assassination it was very suspicious the
way he died
and the fact that there was no autopsy
and so on so dr baba's death also
quite possibly was a targeted
assassination
okay this is a question by aditi
the yakut people in sakha russia are
turkic
what's their culture and beliefs like
how did turkic people make russia as
their home
are the turks and mongols of similar
ethnicity is it different from chinese
why do some races look sibling but far
from
okay but they have different genetics
okay i get the question
let's go back to the good old map
so this is the map let's go to the sakha
republic
which is somewhere here if you can see
my mouse pointer north east of
present-day russia let's take a look at
that
sakai republic russia
so as you can see the this shaded region
in in red is this is the sakha republic
of russia
the people who live there are of turkic
ethnicity uh the russians used to call
them tatars or something or the yakut
people yeah the yakut people that's
right what's written here
so the question is how did such turkic
people make russia as their home
well that's a good question the the
answer is that this was never russia
this was always the rome and the
russians made this part of russia
okay so these people the the yakut
people and other so-called tatar people
and so on they have lived in this region
in these regions siberia etc
for i suppose thousands of years
even before the
ruse or the russians emerged as a
separate uh distinct ethnicity
what eventually happened is that the
russians expanded
see moscow is his is here
so this is the heartland of russia
that's where the
that's the slavic heartland
and
the russians expanded eastwards from
from there
in the past three four hundred years
and eventually they reached all the way
to the eastern
coast of eurasia and they even colonized
alaska in north america
so it is a russian colonization that
ensured that the yakut people became
part of
their territory became part of russia
it was not the other way around that the
yakut people migrated to something that
was already russia
so that's what happened it is russian
colonization that ensured that all of
this region
became part of the
russian empire
uh the turks and the mongols
are of similar ethnicity i think they
have similar they have the same origins
which goes back about two two and a half
thousand years
uh their ancestors were the hunik people
who gave rise to these two ethnicities
who are now separate the mongols and the
turks
they have the same culture the same
beliefs the same so-called religion if
you want to call it religion which is
tangirism which is a polytheistic
religion whose major deity two deities
are the sky father and the earth mother
thingry and umai and there are multi
multiple other deities and gods and
goddesses and spirits and so on in this
belief system it's a polytheistic
polytheistic belief system
so this was the common uh culture of the
turks and the mongols that is the hunik
peoples and slowly these became separate
the turks eventually adopted islam
and that was the history in short of
these two ethnicities
yes they are different from the chinese
the han chinese are different are
different ethnicity or different uh
people from the hunik peoples
uh why do some races look siblings but
they are different in genetics it's
because they all
lived in similar environments
so if you go in the far north of asia of
eurasia you will find that there's a lot
of snow there a lot of ice
and the sunlight is very harsh there it
reflects off the snow and it can cause
snow blindness if too much light goes
into the eyes and therefore the peoples
who lived in all of these regions they
developed smaller eyes to ensure that
they were not blinded by
the reflection of sunlight from the snow
and that's why they look similar but
they clearly have different ethnicities
if you do a genetic
analysis of their ethnicities you will
find
different haplogroups
which i have not gone into personally in
detail
but i expect you will find genetic
differences between these people
so i hope that answers these questions
good question
all right
some other questions let me see if i
have some
other questions okay that's this is a
question from yesterday's
uh list that i was not able to take up
i'll take this one right now
this is by
subhanu
the media is considered to be the fourth
pillar of democracy but indian media is
now divided into two groups
the so-called godi media and the
so-called seculars each having their own
agendas propagandas bias etc what is my
view about this my view is very clear
the media has never been impartial the
me there is no such thing as the fourth
the fourth pillar of democracy they have
created this uh
uh this perception
to increase their importance the media
has always been a tool of propaganda in
the past we did not know about this
because there was no social media to
expose them
but they have always been
a major component of the propaganda
machinery of whoever is in power of the
establishment it's always been that way
they have never been impartial they have
never been unbiased they have never been
the fourth beloved of democracy they
have always been one of the major
pillars of propaganda the media
worldwide including the u.s media
including the indian media
the indian media for decades was simply
a mouthpiece of the uh establishment the
major political party that was in power
since the british raj times
the media has always been a mouthpiece
of that political party today you will
see you have we have seen the emergence
of a different kind of media a more
nationalistic media and they are the
ones that uh the so-called
the leftists and anti-nationals call
them the gudi media or whatever
and the other side calls the other
people seculars so it's always been that
way in the past it was all monochromatic
just one version of the truth was
accepted the official establishment
congress party version of the truth
during the neherubian regime during the
later congress regimes
but in recent times with the emergence
of social media it's become possible
to have media outlets without investing
a lot of money and that's why you have
this newer more nimble more lightweight
media companies that have come up
and these are now labeled as godi media
so it's impossible
for
any media organization to operate
without bias almost impossible i'm not
saying it's hundred percent impossible
it's possible but uh practically it's
never happened
in in real life the real world operation
with if you
under different
principles and so the media has never
been a pillar of democracy it's always
been a pillar of the establishment
and
so that's my view about this the best
thing today is social media even social
media is now taking on flavors five
years ago social media had empowered the
people of india it had given the common
man and woman and child a voice
for the first time in a thousand years
but now as you know there is a lot of
censorship on social media
and again social media has become the
social media companies giants
have become tools
of uh
certain political ideologies i think you
know who they are
so that's how it is so it's
never going to be the case that the
media is going to be unbiased
that it will never have agenda agendas
it will always have agendas it will
always try to
promote propaganda and so on that is
simply the nature of the world
and that's how it is
okay let us take some
[Music]
other questions
okay mahakal says according to the delhi
university books marxism is against
bourgeoisie and pro proletariat which
makes it
seem pro-social welfare but i say maxism
is all about power in just
in which only a handful of people
benefit please elaborate
see marxism
is something that sounds very
intellectual
they have a very interesting
intellectual framework with all kinds of
wonderful dif well defined and in
intelligent sounding terms
the
bourgeoisie the proletariat the
um
the cool i mean they have all these
terms
and it sounds like they have it all
figured out but what actually happens is
that marxism wants to make everybody
equal but some people
are more equal than others and they have
more privileges than others just look at
the history
of the countries where marxist systems
were implemented it's all it's it's all
staring you in the face
the ussr was a marxist socialist
experiment
right
it was a communist country what happened
in the ussr
the ordinary people of the ussr all
had to live in communes
there was no private property
they were all
poor
but a very small number of people the
polit bureau
they lived in ultra
luxurious they lived lives of extreme
luxury and all the power was
concentrated with them
because they knew the real nature of
marxism and they knew how to use it
to gain power and to retain power look
at communist china
the same thing happened with the chinese
communist party
look at cuba look at countries like
angola look at the other countries so
it's if you look at it and examine it
objectively
you will see that the people who benefit
from marxism and what do i mean by
benefit
power
the people who come to power the people
who
who retain
the political power in a marxist system
are a very very very small number of
people
the so-called politburo of the communist
party which is in power and that's how
it always is
but they
they def they justify what they are
doing
by saying the right things we are all
about equality we are all about
prosperity we want everybody to be equal
we want everything to be social welfare
based we are against the bourgeoisie who
are the evil bloodsuckers the vampires
the proletariat of the workers they are
the ones who should be empowered but the
real power empowering happens of
themselves
the real and and they call it the
dictatorship of the proletariat
it which which
implicitly gives them the right to rule
as the dictatorship of the political of
the proletariat because we represent the
proletariat we are the ones who
represent them not you not anybody else
but we represent the proletariat who
decides that they decide it so it's all
about power in the end
and it's always a small number of people
who really understand what maxism is who
benefit from marxism
okay
let's take some other questions
what do i think of freeing temples from
state control they have to be freed from
state control this is non-negotiable the
state has no business interfering in any
any uh religion the constitution is
supposed to be secular right so why do
uh
why why why are temples they are i mean
why are hindu institutions the only
institutions that are under state
control and
they are being stolen from why is that
so
so it it clearly shows you that the
indian state
is a hindu phobic apartheid state they
are controlling
hindu temples they are stealing all the
wealth of the temples and using it for
their secular purposes whatever those
purposes are
so this is unacceptable
and it has to
end
this has to go away and i don't think
that bringing in a new law or something
will do it what needs is we need a new
constitution start from the basics
that's what needs that's what needs to
happen
okay what else do we have
lots of questions
okay rana jargis says what's the major
difference between communism and
socialism is socialism closer to
capitalism
uh
communism is hard socialism so socialism
is soft communism it's essentially the
same thing the ussr which was a
communist country was the union of
soviet socialist republics so uh
socialism is kind of a little bit
gentler more moderate
or they will not force you to give up
all your private property but overall
the laws and the rules and the way the
system is implemented is essentially
going to
to
impose the same kind of end results upon
you in india i think private property is
not regarded as a fundamental right it
is not recognized as a fundamental right
in the indian constitution or laws
private property in india so that is the
uh
consequence of being a socialist country
so socialism and communism is more or
less the same thing it it
it brings about the same kind of end
result uh overall
poverty of the country
the worship of mediocrity
the demonization of quality and talent
and exceptionalism and all that so i'm
not saying that
that capitalism is good or something
capitalism is responsible for the
complete destruction
of the environment and of the earth
the
unbridled
pursuit of quarter upon quarter profits
endless in finite profits on a finite
planet is only going to end up brewing
in ruining the planet
so capitalism is very different from
socialism or communism but communism and
socialism are more or less
different flavors of the same thing
as a student we are taught to cram out
the syllabus but how can a student like
me start exploring on my own and where
to start
ask yourself what are you curious about
what are you interested about what
things interest you what are you
passionate about
and then look for information online
everything is available for for free
online either on youtube or various
websites
so let's say you are interested in
i don't know uh
let's say you're interested in
technology there is so much information
available about technology or or or how
to learn
skills in technology you can uh
you can access entire courses
professional courses online on youtube
on open courseware websites
and so on and so forth so it's all about
pursuing your curiosity following your
curiosity following your interests
and you will have to spend extra time
doing that because most of your time
will be consumed by
your
academic coursework memorizing
memorizing memorizing but try and find
some more time
outside of that
to pursue your interests
and acquire some real world skills so
start online all the information is
available online teach yourself how to
search for information online that is
the most value one of the most valuable
skills you can acquire today
how to search for information online
because the information is there
today in the internet age everything is
available online
some things you may have to pay for but
you can ignore those things because the
same information will be available
elsewhere
for free
so check it out
teach yourself how to
search for information effectively
quickly online
and then go for it and learn whatever
you need to learn or wish to learn
okay why does india not buy the f-35
fighter jet it's a complex situation
first of all it's an extremely expensive
fighter jet you may have to spend
more than a hundred million dollars
on just one jet
so if you want to buy 10 fighter planes
f35 pipelines you may have to spend more
than a billion dollars
and then you may have to you will have
to sign various agreements with the us
uh data sharing agreements which may
impose certain costs on you
data costs you may have to reveal
certain information that you may not
want to really really reveal to the us
it kind of makes you a u.s satellite
state and then they will prevent you
from buying technology and weapons from
other countries because those may
interfere with the f-35 system the
electronic spectrum and all that
and it's not really it may not even be a
very good fighter jet jet you know
uh i would say that instead of see
for the cost of one f-35 fighter jet you
may be able to acquire five or six um
[Music]
more cheaper fighters what is the cost
of a thesis plane let me see
let me try and see what is the cost of
the lca
stages
so this is the lca pages what is the
cost
i'm wondering what is the cost of this
plane
so it's about 26 million
for the mach 1 plane and about 40
million for the mark for the full
operational clearance mark one plane
so for the price of one
uh f35 you will be able to get three lc8
aegis planes and it's not the only jet
that's under the under development we
are
developing
uh multiple jets the uh the thesis mark
ii
the twin engine deck back deck based
fighter the amca also the
next generation plane and so on so i
think it is
much more worthwhile for india to invest
in its own
fighter jet program instead of buying
this f-35 fighter jet which may not even
be a very very good fighter plane it's
not proven in combat
it's had a very very long tedious
development cycle lots of problems in
the development
and
it's had lots of hurdles lots of
problems so i'm not sure how good this
fighter jet is it is the most expensive
fighter jet program in human history
most likely
but i'm not sure how good it is so i
think it's best for india to develop its
own technology
develop a family of fighter jets of its
own
and that would be the best uh
best course of action for the indian
military
there are multiple reasons right like
price and all that
so i think that's what needs to happen
okay karan rao says what will be the
geopolitical situation of the indian
subcontinent and the world at large in
the coming 50 years based on historical
evidence
as it is said that history repeats
itself
so it is uh
it is always
risky to make predict predictions
predictions have a tendency of making
you look stupid in the long run
uh so what i would say is that
if you look at how things are moving
right now on the geopolitical chess
board
it looks like we are uh looking at the
1930s all over again
and
china is now
behaving
like uh germany was behaving in the
1930s
you know becoming a powerful economy
investing
a huge amount of money in the military
in the military
bullying other nations
and all that so the chinese are
exhibiting the same
behavioral
patterns today they are trying to upset
the apple card they want to
displace the us as the preeminent
geopolitical superpower in the world and
so on
so it and right now the chinese economy
is kind of slowing down it's grinding to
a halt which may
send the chinese leadership into panic
mode and they may try to do something
silly or stupid
so what could happen in the next five to
ten years is we may have war in asia
it's quite possible let me try and grab
taiwan i don't know how the americans
will react will they
try to stop the chinese or will they
just give up if they give up then
they're done
if the americans don't
fight
don't resist a chinese
attempt to take over taiwan then their
status as the world's only superpower
will evaporate overnight
so if the chinese try this you may have
war or even world war three in asia
if the chinese don't do that then they
will try to slowly slowly creep forward
and bully all the other nations
around them
grab territory
if they cross india's red lines then we
may have war between india and china
so there are multiple possibilities it
all depends on how the chinese behave
when it comes to india
the indian subcontinent
uh india needs to
once and for all end the terrorist
threat that comes from china from from
from pakistan
all the time
as long as you have pakistan
and the isi and the pakistan army in
power on the western border india will
never have peace the only solution is to
balkanize pakistan hopefully peacefully
i have nothing against the people of
pakistan
the enemy is the isi and the pakistani
army the generals
who have taken this entire country
hostage and they are using it to empower
and enrich themselves using india as the
pretext that india is our mortal enemy
india is not the mortal enemy the real
enemy of the pakistani people is the isi
and the pakistan army
so indian is to ensure that this threat
is dealt with
so hopefully in the next five to ten
years we will see
a solution to the pakistan problem
then we will have peace
in the western border then we can deal
with the chinese threat
so it's not as simple as i make it sound
uh it's all interconnected the pakistani
army and isi is propped up by the
chinese
so it's a complex
and fast evolving situation much of it
will depend on what the chinese
moves are in the next five to ten years
uh
so if the chinese
uh succeed in their ambition of
displacing the us as a superpower then
it's going to be a chinese world for the
next 50 to 100 years
if india emerges as a real power
in the next 10 20 years economic and
military power then the world may be
more balanced
so it also depends on what india does
and what kind of leadership india will
have over the next 10 20 years
so
whom will the indians elect
in the next election a lot depends on
that if you elect certain kinds of
people then india will go backwards
it will go back to the nehru and era so
one hopes that doesn't happen so there's
a lot of
parameters in this
so i can't really predict what can
happen what will happen
i can say what could happen i would like
to see india emerge as an economic and
military
great power in the next 20 years
and it has to start happening in the
next five or 10 years otherwise we will
be too far behind the chinese and they
may be able to have their way with asia
and the world
so i can't
say in detail
exactly what will happen but these are
some of the things that could possibly
happen i would like to see
india emerge as a major power as a
superpower in the next 20 years it is
certainly possible india has the
potential the talent the resources to
become
a superpower in beginning in the next 20
years
so it all depends on the leadership and
what decisions and actions they take
rishikesh dharma sharma says how do i
learn
leadership
well leadership you learn with
experience
uh of course it helps if there is a good
um
a good
book or course about leadership what
leadership actually is but there is no
such book available anywhere there are
books on business leadership and things
like that but that's not real leadership
business leadership is just how to
manage people
that's all it is actually and how to
take people in the right direction and
make them work for your goals and how to
make them invested in your goals but
that is not real leadership real
leadership is something entirely
different
real leadership is
selfless service without anything
without expecting anything in return and
not just that much more than that
so there are lots of aspects to
leadership
of what of what qualities a leader
should develop within himself or herself
to reach the position of a real leader
maybe i should go into that in the
future make a separate video or series
of videos about that but as far as i
know there is no real
uh
book that explains these things there is
no course online
or any academic course that explains or
teaches what leadership actually is
so what you can do to learn leadership
is ask yourself who are the leaders i
admire
ask yourself who are the leaders i
admire in the past hundred years past
thousand two thousand years globally
and then
study their lives in their actions so
that is one way of understanding what
leadership is
what
were their actions what were their
objectives
whom did they serve
what values and
principles did they hold dear
what were the red lines what were the
strategic tactics
if you if you study all that then you
may be able to uncover the patterns
so these are some of the ways of
studying leadership
and
yeah that's what you should do
okay
what else do we have okay let me take
some
older questions
this is by mighty ashish is reservation
right or wrong
well reservations
have good intentions i should say i
should say
the intention is to
give people a better chance at life
people who have traditionally
uh
been under underprivileged
now the way it has been implemented is
just wrong it is done on the basis of
so-called caste
so certain
communities that are classified as
scheduled castes and schedule tribes and
whether other backward task
casts or classes whatever obc's and also
on
they have been given reserve they are
given reservations in the indian system
in the in the academic system in schools
and colleges and universities and jobs
in the government sector and so on so
forth so it is all done on the basis of
of your birth
not on the basis of your financial
condition
the problem is that many people who are
born in these so-called categories
they may be financially quite well-off
and there may be people who are born in
general categories who may be
financially destitute but because they
don't come under this this so whatever
category that's why they are not given
uh the benefits of reservations so what
really needs to happen is that you
should give people
uh
reservations or or financial help based
on financial status only
not on the basis of whatever is the
was the category
that they are born under then you will
have actual
actual uh equality
of opportunity for everybody the
what what they are trying to achieve is
equality of opportunity you can never
have equality of outcome see what is the
difference between equality of
opportunity and equality of outcome let
me show you that
let me bring this
so
this is called equality of opportunity
everybody starts
from the same place
equality of outcome means everybody
finishes at the same place that is
impossible and that is wrong
so
what we need to achieve is giving
everybody the same equal opportunities
of starting from the same place in time
and in place
so if everybody gets the same education
and everybody gets the same access to
education that is equality of
opportunity and from there they can
progress as as for their aptitude and
abilities
so the
what needs to happen is the people who
are financially backward they should be
given financial support and everybody
should be given the same education
so the way to solve this
is to make education
freely accessible to everybody
make education free for all
today what we have is that we have we
are seeing the commercialization of
education
which is just wrong it should not happen
in a civilized society so reservations
may have the right intent
but the way they are implemented is
terrible it's causing more divisions in
society it is creating more problems
than solving problems so the way it
needs to be implemented is
is is very different from the way it's
being done today
education should be free for all
and so should health care in a civilized
society education and health care should
be free for all all citizens
okay let us take a few more questions
okay i'm trying to find
i saw something it disappeared
just a second
okay let's take this question
uh rohan says i heard an update about
india's autonomous underwater vehicle
a drone submarine a project that is
jointly being done with
larson and tobru what are your views on
this
i think it's a good thing
uh
autonomous vehicles whether these are
aerial vehicles or underwater vehicles
are the future
uh
of
of millet of the military of warfare so
india needs to be proactive in investing
in these technologies
and i haven't uh read this news i have
i'm not aware of this in great detail
i'm aware that some such project is
underway
what we need is we need multiple such
projects underway why develop only one
vehicle when you can develop an entire
class or an entire family of vehicles
the chinese have developed hundreds
of autonomous
aerial vehicles drones they've been
doing this for the past 10 15 20 years
we only have a couple of such projects
in india the rustom drone or whatever it
is
and i'm not sure if anything else is
being developed maybe things are being
developed that are under wraps which
would be a good thing
my view is very clear we need to invest
heavily in these technologies the
technologies of the future
what india is right now doing is trying
to catch up with the technologies of the
1990s and 2000s
which is good but we need to invest more
in this so that we can start developing
the technologies of the future which is
autonomous vehicles drones and all that
so if this is happening it is a very
good thing i'm very happy about this we
need
more emphasis
on underwater drones aerial drones
robotics ai augmented reality and all
these associated 21st century
next generation
technologies
chanakya says what happens when
what has been long a soft state
tries to become a hard state
and the setbacks it can face from its
own people does it cause a chaotic
period not necessarily
so what we mean by a soft state is a
state that does not pursue its national
interest which is india india is like a
punching bag
india has been for most of its post 1947
history been a punching bag
the pakistanis keep attacking india in
various ways and india just keeps
absorbing the punches without making
them pay a heavy price for it so india
has always been a soft state india
always emphasizes on soft power which is
nonsense india has not developed it its
hard power to the extent that it should
have
so india meets the definition of a soft
state
it is likely that today in 2021 november
india may be
in the process
of making a transition from a soft state
to a hard state it is possible such
things are done quietly in secrecy
and so it is a good thing what happens
when you do this it is done quietly in
secrecy you do not reveal what you are
doing you do not you do not reveal your
plans to the world
you do it quietly
and you announce it when its a faith
accompli when it's done
so what are the setbacks it can face
from its own people when you have
when you have uh the old establishment
which made india a soft state then they
will try to resist
any attempt
for the state to harden itself
and then they have an entire ecosystem
the media and the professors the
academia who will try and portray this
as fascism as bad
they will write articles against this in
global
especially american and british
uh
publications they will demonize the
government they will
uh portray it as being fascist and this
phobic or that phobic
non-inclusive
and so on and so forth so
they will what they will do is they will
try and create this
impression
this narrative
that the soft state which is now trying
to become a hard state is doing this
with malified intentions malified
intentions internally and externally so
india will be portrayed as an aggressor
towards smaller countries like nepal
towards sri lanka india will be
portrayed as a bully for whatever reason
even though india has never bullied
anybody
and india the indian government will be
portrayed as a fascist government
even though it doesn't meet any of the
definitions of fascism so this is the
kind of setback it can face from its own
people and other things are like
internal disruptions like the farmer
protests and all that which are aimed at
destabilizing and weakening the
government and hopefully bringing it
down in the next election
so these are the things that are done
to engineer
a regime change from within and without
the country from from inside the country
and from outside the country all of
these forces are funded
organized and orchestrated from
somewhere outside
so these are the things that happen
when a soft state tries to become a hard
state and starts
trying to pursue
its own
national interest
all the hyenas jackals and vultures
start circling all the dogs start
barking and biting
and it takes great leadership
to survive that phase so that's what we
are
seeing right now
and it will take great leadership to
take india to the next phase and
make it a proper
hard state
and hopefully
a superpower in the future
okay let me take some other questions
says why after the parliament attack
attack did india not declare war on
pakistan
and the government was under uttar
bihari vajpayee and what were the
intelligence bureau and raw
doing
so india did not attack
declare war in pakistan of the after the
parliament attack because india is a
soft state
india has always been a soft state even
mr vajpayee
even mr vajpayee was not very different
from the previous prime ministers of
india
i think one of the great prime ministers
of india which i have not spoken about
much
is a
was
mr pv narasimha
i think he was one of the great prime
minister of india
and he pulled india out of chaos and his
his contributions are not quite
recognized that is a digression but
india should have made pakistan pay a
very heavy price
for the parliament attack which mr
when was the parliament attack which
year was it let me take a look
so i think it was in 2001
and clearly mr vajpayee was in power at
the time so there was this this
operation parakram or something there
was this war game that was played in
and the
armed forces of india were placed on
high alert
on the western border
on the pakistan border and the pakistani
forces also were given time to come and
face india and so on but
at the end of the day it was all just an
exercise in optics
and pakistan was not made to pay a price
for what it did for trying to attack
the heart of india's
governance the parliament and that
emboldened pakistan when somebody does
something like that they have to be made
to pay a price and if they don't pay the
price then they will become bolder and
they will try
something even more audacious
and that's what happened in in 2008 in
mumbai and there were many bomb blasts
in between men and terrorist attacks uh
mumbai 2008 there were mumbai 2006 or
something bomb blasts train blasts many
people lost their lives again the
pakistanis did that and again they were
not made to pay for this they were blast
in delhi other places so this is the
definition of a soft state
the indian politicians
lacked the will the courage
to take
actions in favor of india's natural
interest i don't know what is the reason
for this
i simply don't understand
so now things have changed
and hopefully it is changing it is going
to change further in india will
finally
become the country that it
always has needed to be
so one hopes that is the case
okay
uh some other questions let me see
arnold says do you think uh gunnami baba
was natalia washington
i truly believe that netaji was so that
gumnami baba was subhash and i also
uh
have the strong feeling that uh the
gentleman known as gum nambi baba
was actually nithajay subhashin rabos i
believe that is most likely the case
and i think anu's there has written has
done a great deal of research about this
and has even written a book or multiple
books i'm not sure i haven't had the
time to read any of his works i it is
something that i
would like to do in the future if i can
find the time
but yes i think it is quite likely that
gumnami baba was netaji
it's quite likely i think
aruna says is there any truth in
calculus calculus originating in india
or
was it exclusively invented by newton
considering leibniz also is said to have
developed it first
and newton's feud with robert hook
so newton's feud with robert hook is a
different story newton was a petty and
jealous person robert hook
was
a brilliant scientist who was totally
marginalized by newton
his robot hook's portrait doesn't even
survive today because newton had it
removed and destroyed
so newton was a very petty and
vindictive person
now
where did calculus originated india
where did calculus originate india or
in england
or in germany limits calculus originated
in india
in the kerala school of mathematics at
least a century before newton and
leibniz discovered it at the same time
okay so it is the kerala school of
mathematics that has been demonstrated
and proven to have
developed calculus
at least a century before newton and
leibniz and this
knowledge
was stolen from india by jesuit priests
who brought it to europe
and it is no coincidence that newton and
leibniz both came across calculus
and both published their first works and
calculus in the same year the same thing
the same year i mean what sort of a
coincidence is that
so it's clear that it was developed in
india it was stolen by the jesuits and
transmitted to europe
so newton or leibniz neither of them
discovered calculus it was the indians
it was the kerala school of mathematics
okay what other questions do we have
okay rohan says hydrogen fuel cell
electric vehicles
versus lithium-ion battery electric
vehicles which or any other battery
electric vehicle which one is the real
future
for
bev
we need to overhaul our entire
our whole entire power transmission
systems
uh still we need hfc for heavy vehicles
and other machinery what's my view i
think the hydrogen fuel cell
is not as efficient
as a lithium ion or other kind of
battery
i think the hydrogen fuel cell also
needs liquid
it has a liquid component to it if i'm
not mistaken it's been a long time since
i
uh
studied this technology but i think from
the sense that i get is what i what i
think is that
uh the future is in lithium ion and
other other solid batteries
hydrogen fuel cells may not quite be the
future they may not be as efficient or
as
easy to transport and use
than these solid batteries like the
lithium-ion batteries
so that is
going to be the future
and that's the direction that the
various uh
electric vehicle manufacturers have
taken
for example tesla tesla is is investing
heavily in lithium-ion batteries they
have developed and
developed the technology
and made it quite advanced iteratively
they started with this standard
batteries that they purchased
from various suppliers but then slowly
over time they started developing their
own batteries and now they are
constructing this gigafactory i think
it's in texas or somewhere else
somewhere in the u.s which will produce
enormous quantities of these batteries
and these will also be used in heavy
vehicles like pickup trucks suvs and
proper large
large long-haul trucks
so the technology is going to be
good enough
to power a very heavy vehicles
so i think that is the future hydrogen
fuel cells are no longer being
considered uh as far as as i know very
seriously
for powering electric vehicles i think
it's
it's the solid batteries like the
lithium-ion batteries that are the
future most likely
okay let us take one more question
they just says sapience supports the rn
invasion theory how can you support it
well i have my own intelligence
i have my own
i have done my own studies
i know what the evidence is
i don't care what sapience says if so
and so a person supports it it doesn't
mean that i have to blindly support it
it's as simple as that how can i support
it because i want to because i trust my
own intelligence right that's why i
support
the aryan invasion theory
what exactly is the question
sapiens supports the rn invasion theory
how can you support it how can i support
it
so
what am i supporting am i supporting
sapiens
or am i supporting the aryan invasion
theory
what is the question i don't support the
iron vision theory i think all of you
know that by now
do i support sapiens
well i haven't
i don't remember saying that i support
sapiens
i haven't read the book i have it
somewhere i haven't read it i haven't
had the time to read it the thing is
most of the history books
that are available anywhere they support
the rn invasion theory i have a separate
video on this channel in which i have
given uh
recommendations of history books and i
have also said that most of these
history books will support the
orientation theory you have to be aware
of that
so let's say you have a history book
that is a really good history book but
the author supports the iron vision
theory what are you going to do
what i would say is don't read that part
but read the other other sections of the
book which actually have good history
right which are written well
that is the problem you you're always
going to face
that uh
most of the history books mainstream
mystery books support the orientation
theory but they also
have
good depictions of other parts of
history
so that's what i would say
okay
let's take something else
uh should we remove the word secular
from our preamble we should remove the
constitution haven't have a new
constitution that's what needs to happen
okay there's clarifying he was telling
somebody else in the chat about that
okay got it
got it
okay what else do we have i'll take
maybe one or two more questions
shaker salaf says what is your take on
shashi thorough shashi tarou's work
works on history i haven't read any of
those
so
what can i say
maybe he's a good writer maybe
but we all know what his uh
what his opinions are he is a great
supporter of mr gandhi and mr nehru and
the nerubian regime he thinks that
that's the best thing that ever happened
to india he's a great supporter of the
indian constitution which is so foreign
and colonial
so it tells me everything i need to know
about the person
and once i know that i'm not gonna waste
my time reading his works in history
so i
i expect that some of the things that he
has written about may be good maybe he's
a good writer maybe his style of writing
is good and maybe some of the chapters
in whatever works he has
may actually be factual and some
sections may be good but overall i know
what tone he's going to take i know i
know overall what thesis is going to put
forth
is going to put forth the thesis
that
india was essentially born in 1947
and uh
the neherubian regime was the best thing
that happened to us the congress party
was great
the british did loot india but they did
a good great deal of good also for us
and we need to worship gandhi and nehru
and the congress regime and we need to
go back in the direction because that is
the right idea of india that is going to
be the overall thesis that he is going
to put forth and that's why i have no
interest
in reading his works on history
so that's
the the
uh the
what i would like to say or what i can
say
about mr tharu's work without having
read any of those
were horses killed in the ashwamedha
yagna yes at the end of the ashwamedha
yagna there was a horse sacrifice
yes
all right
swastika says as is absolute peace
possible
well
we are currently living as joe rogan
would say in kaliyug and in kali-yuga
absolute peace is not possible
we have too many evil ideologies
supremacist ideologies exclusivist
ideologies expansionist ideologies in
force in the world today and in that
scenario in that environment absolute
peace is not possible
maybe if you can turn the cycle of yugas
around and bring satyayug back
then absolute peace may be possible for
a certain period of time until the cycle
of yuga's
changes
again
so if you look at the overall
history of the human species you will
see that we are a very
aggressive warlike species and overall
we have been typically at war with each
other
at conflict with each other we are
overall a violent species it's only when
we civilize ourselves with the right
kind of culture
it's only then
that peace can prevail
but that's not going to be universally
globally possible because you will
always have
certain other belief systems that will
be expansionist aggressive
exclusivist supremacists and so on and
so forth
so i think it's it's very hard to
envisage a future
or a present in which you will have
absolute peace it's simply not possible
i don't think so at least in the world
that we live in today
okay
is there any other question maybe i can
take one more question
this is by charmi is it possible to
trace back the history of a certain clan
if so what are the general ways to do so
see in the west you have all the
genealogy which means that they trace
back your ancestry based on various
records
that are available in churches and other
places
in india i think it was there before all
our great libraries were burned down
today we have lost the written records
of of various clans
i think in various rajput clans you had
these bards
or these uh
family uh
chroniclers who would keep records of
the
people who lived at various points in
time in a in a certain clan so if that
survives in some places then you may be
able to trace back the history and
lineage of that particular clan
it may be possible in some cases but
overall we have lost
the written records of our lineages of
our history of the various clans
so
maybe one could
speak to the elders of a certain clan
and see what memories they have
and we could try and record that but to
a large extent we have unfortunately
lost
the hard written records of our past to
a large extent
so general ways to do that is through
genetics test your genetics but for that
you need a proper divide
wide broad and deep genetic study of the
whole
overall genetics of india which has not
been undertaken there is not even a
single plan to do that
so if you have that sort of data
countrywide nationwide subcontinent-wide
genetic data then you may be able to
test your own dna and see where you fit
into that and maybe that could give you
a general
idea
of your
deep lineages
patrilineal as well as matrilineal
lineages
so that what can happen in the future as
of today it's very hard to trace back
the history of most clients of most
lineages
that's where we are
today
all right i think we have reached the
end of today's session
so thank you everybody as always a great
pleasure
talking to you all taking your questions
answering your questions
and we're going to continue doing that
next week
and to those of you whose questions i
have not been able to answer i apologize
there are thousands of you there's only
one of me
and there's only this much time i do my
best i will try and keep doing my best
and keep asking your questions
and i'll keep answering thank you very
much all of you for your support for
your viewership
and
i will see you once again very soon next
week thank you very much
bye